Ray
Man 1: Dalio, thank you very much. We spoke last year in exactly this place. And you outlined in part kind of the cycle that you see in civilizations vying for supremacy of
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): the world. And not everyone I think kind of bought into your views on this. And you were derided as Jeremiah's scaring people and
Man 1: everything a year
later.
Man 1: You have a new summary of ideas that you've been formulating for a long time out this week and about 18 people have sent it to me. And
so I
Man 1: think we've reached a moment where people are ready to hear what you're saying. So if you wouldn't mind outlining
in whatever
Man 1: detail you like the cycle that you see the countries go through and where our country,
Speaker 3: the U.S. is in that cycle.
Speaker 4: Gladly. Yeah, so there's...
Speaker 4: There's a cycle,
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): there are orders, there are systems, right? So there's a monetary order.
How does
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): the economy work? You put in money, creates credit, people with credit do things with that, they borrow, if they can earn enough money to pay back, the system works well, they create productivity, they create opportunities, the capital markets and so on. That's the monetary system. And the way that works,
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): in the cycle is that when there's no debt, such as in 1945, we start a new monetary order, there's no debt, there's a system, and it builds up over a period of time, and it's a mechanics that when income, when debt service payments rise relative to incomes, it squeezes out other spending, the way it would do for you
as an
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): individual, the way it would do for companies,
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): except governments can print money. But that squeezes out spending and that becomes a problem. And then you also have a supply-demand problem. So when you have a new monetary system, which the United States had the new monetary system, and the dollar was the world's reserve currency, then you can sell a lot more of the debt.
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): So there's a supply and a demand, right? And so when that builds up and everybody's one man's debts or another man's assets and they build up holding a lot of dollar-denominated debt and then they sell a lot more debt, then there's a mechanics of that supply-demand. And then when you have politics and world politics, geopolitics enter into it.
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): That monetary system is more at risk for those reasons. We'll get into that. But the first force of these five forces is the mechanics of this process, which is the monetary system. The second is there's a domestic political order. All countries have an order, a system, and all these orders change and they evolve. And of course, that is connected to the economic system. And so when you get large wealth and values differences,
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): And there's a sense that the system isn't working for them and there's greater polarity. There's the emergence of populism, like in the 30s, you know, the left and the right. And there's that populism gets to the point that there are irreconcilable difference. In other words, the lack of willingness to compromise, the lack of willingness to accept loss, losing one's vote and so on. But if fight and win for me at all coincides.
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): Like in the 30s, four democracies chose to be autocracies because the polarity was so great and the willingness to go along with that democracy system ceased to exist. So that dynamic has happened throughout history.
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): And then the third is the geopolitical order, how countries work relative to each other. What's the system? And after World War II, we created a system, a multilateral system, in which it was in some ways naive, but it was very different than existed before,
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): In that, by being multilateral, having United Nations, a World Trade Organization, a World Health Organization, a World Court, and all of those, the idea of being representative and they would make decisions in a certain rule-based system was the path. And, of course, the problem of that is that any system has to have its enforcement.
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): And if the system as a whole, a multilateral system, is not consistent with the interests of those who are the most powerful, the power rules, and so you have the dynamic of the breaking down of that order, right? So we're breaking down the monetary order in a very classic way. We're breaking down the political order in a very classical way. We're breaking down the geopolitical order. So those orders, we have to recognize throughout time, all of those orders have changed.
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): There's never been a time that they haven't changed and haven't broken down in their issues, and they're getting back to how they were in some ways in the past. Number four is acts of nature. Drought, floods, and pandemics have killed more people than wars, so you can't ignore it as a big influence. And number five is the inventions of new technologies, particularly fabulous new technologies come about, and they're important not only for prosperity, but they're important in wars. You know?
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): Whoever wins the tech war wins also the economic and the geopolitical war. And so there's that dynamic. And that dynamic is when there's rising powers, challenging and existing powers. There's no court to go to. There's no way of resolving that. There are tests of these powers, and we're in a power type of dynamic. Now, when you understand that that dynamic works through time, and you get down to its individual symptoms. In other words,
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): In my book, Principles for Dealing with the Changing World Order, which I wrote about five years ago, I took and I broke that cycle into five parts of the six parts of the cycle. And like a disease, you can see the symptoms in those parts and you can see it progress and you can see the choices that exist at those stages. So when you're in a different stage, the leadership has a different stage.
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): stage and all I wanted to do it whether it's in that book or in our conversation here today is to try to let people see that and and I'm just a practical
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): investor, right? I've been, for 60 years, I've been a macro investor. So I have to bet on what the future is going to be like. I place financial bets on that. And now I'm at a stage in life that I want to pass that along. So I hope that we could talk about or look at that in a dispassionate way to say, how does the machine work to produce that dynamic?
Speaker 6: That's exactly
Speaker 7 (lower-pitched voice): right. And you're not casting judgments here. You're just
Speaker 7 (lower-pitched voice): Acknowledging what has happened and what therefore is likely to happen. Can I just go back, I don't wanna let
Man 8: this pass. In the second factor that you described in this, the political factor, you pointed back to the very fraught decade of the 1930s. And you said you had four democracies become or revert to autocracies because of the partisanship that became unworkable. They couldn't reconcile and so they became autocratic. Is that a consistent
Speaker 9: principle, do you think? Yeah.
Speaker 9: You can look at it through Chinese dynasties.
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): You can look at it through Rome. Like, who is in control, right? You know, Caesar in the Senate and being stabbed in the Senate. Plato wrote about this, I think it was like...
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): 350 BC, he wrote about the cycle in the republic, in other words, democracies, and the challenge of democracies where you vote and so on, but then there's the wealth gaps and the rich gaps, and then who has the money, and then the not willing to vote, and then there's the power that changes, yes. So
Speaker 7 (lower-pitched voice): partisanship becomes gridlock, becomes irreconcilable, just mass, and then that evolves by necessity into
Man 8: autocracy.
Speaker 11 (lower-pitched voice): Right.
Speaker 11 (lower-pitched voice): When I'm no longer willing to accept that the system, the rule of the
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): system, because everybody thinks it's rigged, okay? The Supreme Court, is it rigged because that partisan has more appointees and it won't be fair? And so I remember when the Supreme Court was kind of the Supreme Court, and we lived in a time where we said the system is fair. The legal system, when you go
in
Speaker 12: and you're convicted, okay, is the legal system fair? Yeah.
Speaker 12: And so on, and then you believe in that system with
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): its imperfections and so on. When that ceases to be the case, when the causes that people are behind are more important to them than the system, the system is in jeopardy, right?
Speaker 9: Yes.
Of
Speaker 7 (lower-pitched voice): course, by definition, and all of this is relevant to where we are now. So tribalism, whether it's political or ethnic. But when people square off into tribes and they have no
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): common ground and they have no hope of reconciling or
Speaker 3: compromising, then you're getting a new system.
Speaker 12: And you see it, it's so interesting. It's like watching a movie over and over and
Speaker 11 (lower-pitched voice): over again. Because then you see how it is they make stereotypes of the other.
Speaker 11 (lower-pitched voice): The stereotype of that personality, the stereotype of that type, whether it's an ethnic or economic or whatever it is, oh, they're one of those, and I'm one
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): of these. And now it becomes the stereotypes that are fighting, right?
Which are
Speaker 15: non-human, right? So it's easier to...
-
Speaker 9: There's no empathy. - Of course, 'cause it's not a human being,
Speaker 16: it's a stereotype.
Speaker 9: - It's the fight. - Right. - And so then you have to pick a side. I mean, one of three things. You have to
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): pick a side and fight for it, or you keep your head down and hope you don't get shot or
Speaker 12: flee throughout history. Yeah, and that's what's happening.
Hate
Speaker 17: to brag, but we're pretty confident this show is the most vehemently pro-dog podcast you're ever going to see. We
can take or
Speaker 17: leave some
Speaker 18 (lower-pitched voice): people, but dogs are non-negotiable. They are the best. They really are our best friends. And so for that reason, we're thrilled to have a new partner called Dutch Pet. It's the fastest growing pet telehealth service. Dutch.com is on a mission to create what you need, what you actually need. Affordable, quality veterinary care anytime, no matter where you
are.
Speaker 18 (lower-pitched voice): they will get your dog or cat what you need immediately it's offering an exclusive discount dutch is for our listeners you get 50 bucks off your vet care per year visit dutch.com slash tucker to learn more use the code tucker for 50 off that is an unlimited vet visit 82 a year 82 bucks a year we actually use this dutch has vets who can handle any pet under any circumstance
in a
Speaker 18 (lower-pitched voice): 10-minute call. It's pretty amazing, actually. You never have to leave your house. You don't have to throw the dog in the truck. No wasted time waiting for appointments. No wasted money on clinics or visit fees. Unlimited visits and follow-ups for no extra cost, plus free shipping on all products for up to five pets. It sounds amazing like it couldn't be real, but it actually is real. Visit dutch.com slash Tucker to learn more. Use
Speaker 19: the code Tucker for 50 bucks off your veterinary care per year.
Speaker 19: Your dogs, your cats, and
your
Speaker 10: wallet will thank you. So you join effectively the civil war, you try and find a safe place
Speaker 20: domestically, or you just split?
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): Yeah, in other words, you're quiet because you don't want to get into the fight. You're going to get injured, right? A lot of people are scared now, right? People you'd imagine never would be scared.
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): They don't want to speak up or something. So you keep your head down. You either get in the fight and fight, pick a side and fight for it. Throughout history, this is true. Pick a side and fight for it or keep your head down or in some cases flee.
you
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): know, people leave, they go from, you know, immigration. Think about how all the immigration largely is taking place. There's some hell taking place in there, and then they move to someplace else where there's not. Here we are in the UAE, okay?
A
Speaker 11 (lower-pitched voice): lot of people are coming to the UAE because they're fleeing in a sense. So there's that dynamic. And so you can see many, many, many symptoms. Like there were things,
Speaker 11 (lower-pitched voice): You know, when it
Speaker 22 (lower-pitched voice): gets violent and when you get killing too many people.
Then you
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): start to cross the lines, you know, like maybe in Iran, okay, do we cross the lines and then where you, you know, there are these symptoms
Speaker 22 (lower-pitched voice): that and there's financial, you know, how do you pay?
So
Speaker 22 (lower-pitched voice): anyway, I'm rambling, but-
Speaker 23: No, you're not rambling. But just
Speaker 7 (lower-pitched voice): back to the political one last question, is it ever resolved? Does the system ever stay intact when you get to a point where people just
Speaker 24: don't wanna compromise at all or even live in the same place?
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): Have you seen any example of where people sort of decide,
Man 1: wait a second, let's enter into power sharing and pull back before this gets violent or we get a
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): king?
So in
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): some places, sometimes in dynasties and so on, they're not often, what happens is there's a reversal or a fixing by somebody who can not, who's strong enough to deal with the issues.
For
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): example, we have a debt issue. We have all of these other issues and can bring people together. But there needs to be almost, Plato would say, the benevolent despot. Yes. And that's in his cycle. In other words, there's somebody who can stop the fighting and
and
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): be smart, and impose the disciplines that are necessary. For example, there's a financial discipline. How do we deal with the debt and all the supply demand and so on? Can we raise taxes? Can we cut spending? What are we going to do to bring about a budget balance, or not a
Speaker 25 (lower-pitched voice): budget a deficit balance, let's say a deficit of 3%
of GDP,
Speaker 25 (lower-pitched voice): would
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): sustain the set of circumstances. What is that financial discipline? What is that way of working together so we do not do each other harm? Because we are at a point, let's say, as we come to the next midterm elections, and there's a significant probability that the Republicans would lose the house,
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): talk of even could be the senate okay now when you go after that and you imagine what the conflict can be like how will that conflict work will it be rule of law or will it be a win at all cost and as that win at all cost and what that means um it is there rules is there playing by the rules
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): you know, that dynamic. So this thing is repeated. It's not easy to get to that point because you have to deal with, you know, how do we stop fighting with each other? And how do we do the right things to get strong? And that's a great challenge in history.
Speaker 7 (lower-pitched voice): So where are we now, given the five factors that you outlined, where is the United States or even
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): really the West will include Europe in this very familiar cycle of rise
Speaker 22 (lower-pitched voice): and fall?
In
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): my book, I show 18 measures of health having to do with education, military, reserve currency, a number of measures that show strength. Okay, what is the level of strength?
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): And the United States is the strongest power which has been in relative decline and experiencing these conflicts. And that's measured, if you go in the book, How Principles for Dealing with the Changing World Order, you'll see a number of charts.
So I
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): don't want to just pronounce it that way. I just want to say...
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): that like if you were to take education and you take scores, pieces, scores, and so on in statistics, you will see that there are rising powers, there are declining powers, there are large wealth and values differences, and we are in what I call stage five,
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): which means we are sort of at the brink, but not over the brink. In other words, we're not, there's a capacity to, it's before a period of great disorder when there can be a monetary breaking down of the system. You know, what is money? We should talk at some point. What is money and can money be an effective storehold of wealth and what happens if it's not?
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): And so we are at what I would call stage five in a six stage cycle. The sixth stage is when there's a breaking down of these orders. We're not there yet, but we are close to there and headed in that type of direction.
What does a
Speaker 26: breakdown look like? What does stage six look like?
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): Well, from the monetary point of view,
it is that there are
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): The demand for the reserve currency is not sufficient to meet the supply. So what that means is you see a supply-demand problem. You produce a lot of supply, and the demand's inadequate. And all things being equal, there will be a rising long rate
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): While the central bank is trying to hold that from down by easing the short rate and And look shortening the maturity of the debt that it sells okay that dynamic and that then the currency The these debts and the currency falls relative to the non fiat currencies in other words like gold in other words You are seeing a movement
by
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): central banks and countries to hold gold as an alternative reserve currency, partially because of that supply-demand situation and partially because they worry
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): That there may be a payments problem and the payments problem like it happened in Japan prior to World War Two. You had an economic problem and the United States sanctioned essentially didn't pay the Japanese money.
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): their debt the money in terms of that like a debtor creditor problem and they didn't make those payments much like russia you know you um they they basically took control because they have the ability to take control of the treasuries and other things and so there is becomes more of a uh reluctance to hold that money as that and a movement more into
uh
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): the non-fiat currency, which
Speaker 27 (lower-pitched voice): is gold.
So
Speaker 10: in other words, other countries perceive a risk
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): in holding dollars because,
Man 8: well, for lots of reasons, but one of them is if the United States government at the time doesn't like you, they can grab your dollars. That's right. So it's not worth it.
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): Right, and it's a risk that both the debtor and the creditor have to each other. So think about it,
China.
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): And if you were thinking China, how do you feel about holding Treasury bonds? Okay. So you may not feel secure about holding Treasury bonds, both for two reasons, because you could be sanctioned, or you also because there's a supply-demand problem. So you start to see the movement in that direction. And then of course, it's also in that situation, governments want to control their supply-demand,
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): So they might establish foreign exchange controls. They might do certain things like that. But they also feel vulnerable. The United States can feel vulnerable if they can't sell enough of those bonds to others, if the demand isn't, because then interest rates would have to rise because of the supply demand, too much supply relative to the demand. To make it more appealing to buyers. Yes, and also to cut the demand for credit.
in
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): other words if the price rise then people will borrow less and so on and that then has the effect of mechanically slowing down the economy that produces that result which so then what happens is then the central bank comes in and it prints money and it buys the debt which depreciates the currency that's the mechanics
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): That's of the debt part of it that is related to the political and the geopolitical part of it that I'm answering your question.
May I
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): just ask
Speaker 29 (lower-pitched voice): you
Speaker 7 (lower-pitched voice): something? So if foreign countries don't wanna buy your debt and your central bank decides we're gonna print more money and buy our own debt with it, which is
Speaker 30 (lower-pitched voice): what we're doing. Wouldn't the people doing that stop and say, wait a second, this sounds like an electric windmill. Like, what are we doing here? This sounds crazy.
Speaker 31: They're stuck.
They're
Speaker 31: stuck. They're stuck because they have
a
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): deficit. And
the deficit
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): will be there unless they raise taxes and cut spending or something.
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): And that's bad for the economy and it's politically bad. - Yes. - Okay. Or you print the money and you make up the difference.
Speaker 27 (lower-pitched voice): And so since the breakdown of the monetary system in 1971, that was when there were too many claims on gold and we had a system attached to gold. And because they were in August 15th, 1971,
Speaker 27 (lower-pitched voice): i remember well i was clerking on the floor
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): of the new york stock exchange after my after college before i went to graduate school richard nixon gets on august 15th sunday night he gets on the television and he says um we're not going to uh allow the conversion of that paper money into gold and we're not going to you won't get your
Speaker 27 (lower-pitched voice): gold
And
Speaker 27 (lower-pitched voice): I walked on the floor of the stock exchange the next morning. I thought this is a big crisis. And what they did is they
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): essentially printed and then we had the stagflation of the 70s. But I was very surprised and I found out I didn't never threw anything like that before I studied history. I found out they did
Speaker 27 (lower-pitched voice): the exact same thing in March. Roosevelt did the exact same thing in March of 1933.
Right
Speaker 33: after he got inaugurated.
Speaker 27 (lower-pitched voice): Right.
Speaker 27 (lower-pitched voice): Okay, for the same reasons. Okay, because your choice is to have a lot of defaults and a debt problem or to do
that, right?
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): That's how it works. That's how the machine works. So, and at the end of the day, since 1971, when we went off the gold standard and we went
to a
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): fiat monetary system, we have always done that, you know, and, you know, the Fed put,
you know,
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): And, you know, that's the way it is.
Speaker 29 (lower-pitched voice): And it's kind of worked for 55 years, but it's showing signs of breaking down.
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): Well, what it
does is
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): it's like using the hair of the dog that bit you.
Speaker 19: Oh, it's the hangover cure. Yeah, I'm familiar with that. Okay, me too.
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): Yeah, for sure.
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): What you do is you give more money in credit. And what happens is to get out of it and because then you make it easier to pay the debt. You make like in 2008 or 2020, you give the money, okay? And you give the credit
and
Speaker 11 (lower-pitched voice): you fund it and you make that, but that makes the debts go up again, okay? Until then you reach the point where the debt,
Speaker 11 (lower-pitched voice): It's squeezing on
Speaker 12: the expenditures and you have the supply demand. So that's why you have these big debt cycles, you know?
When
Speaker 34 (lower-pitched voice): we started this company, we promised that we would only partner with other companies that share our values. We didn't want to advertise products made by people who hate us or, for that matter, you. So with that in mind, it is a pleasure to announce that we're working with Charity Mobile. It is a pro-life phone company.
Speaker 34 (lower-pitched voice): Charity Mobile holds a view on abortion that almost every single major US company disagrees with. They think it's completely wrong. It is sad and celebrating it is one of the darkest things this country's ever done. We agree completely. So when you switch your cell phone service to this American company, they'll donate a percentage of your monthly price plan to a pro-life, pro-family charity that you choose. There's no better way to prove what their real values are than doing that.
Speaker 34 (lower-pitched voice): No one would do that unless they meant it. All their plans are under 50 bucks, and you can keep your existing number and your existing phone if it's compatible. Charity Mobile is a pro-life company serving pro-life customers and supporting pro-life causes and has done it for more than 30 years. Visit charitymobile.com slash Tucker. Use promo code Tucker to get a free phone with free activation, free shipping, and a free gift with every new line of service.
So I
Speaker 35: think even people who are not really interested in monetary policy
or
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): macroeconomics feel like there is a point at which this doesn't work anymore. It just breaks. It is, it's happened all in all. So what does that look like specifically, the debt
Speaker 36: crisis people keep talking?
Speaker 22 (lower-pitched voice): Well, because of that,
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): my last book, my most recent book put out about a little less than a year ago, is called How Countries Go Broke, The Big Cycle.
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): And what I wanted to do is to just show 35 cases of it. That is just the mechanics to show how it works, OK? But it is that dynamic of the squeezing on the spending and the supply demand. And then you start to see it where, as I was saying, the long rate goes up while the short rate comes down because the central bank's pushing the short rate down.
and
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): then they shorten the maturities of the debt, and then the central bank buys that, and then the central bank, now it owns all these treasuries, and then the central bank starts losing money, because
Speaker 12: they own the treasuries, and they're going up. So they have to produce the money and credit to keep that...
Speaker 12: rate down, and they lose more and more money. And that dynamic then doesn't stop the change
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): in the capital flows. That's why you, and then traditionally in all of these cases, you see a move to the hard money, the move to gold, okay, as we're seeing, you see that dynamic in terms of that move to gold.
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): And then it starts to run its course. So it's very much like think about what happened from '71 through the '70s produces more stagflation. And then at some point, the inflation problem or the devaluation of money problem becomes such that the central bank then tightens money and so on. And the Volcker years, 1979, '80, '81, '82.
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): So the pendulum swings. Think about it this way, in order to have a balance, a successful economy, a successful capital market, since one man's debts or another man's assets, you have to keep
Speaker 11 (lower-pitched voice): interest rates not so high that they crush the debtor without having them
so low,
Speaker 11 (lower-pitched voice): that they are bad
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): for the creditor. Right.
So you
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): see these cycles. When we had zero interest rates and negative real interest rates, what you saw was massive creation of credit and money and borrowing and so on.
And
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): then you had that that cycle. So that's what the cycle looks like if you have losses. And then you also have under those circumstances classically the weakening of the central bank's control. Or I should say the strengthening of the central government's control over the central bank. In other words, when these things happen...
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): then there is, they can't be at odds, okay? And so there is greater control by
Speaker 39: the central government of this. And- Are you writing the news? No, I've just seen this movie before. This is exactly what's happening. I
Speaker 12: know, but that's what I'm saying. Because it must happen in the nature of that dynamic when you
have,
Speaker 12: Imagine the
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): fight between the central bank and the central government in the middle of a crisis and so on. So there is this control because there's a monetary thing.
Speaker 40: There has to be.
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): Right. What happens if you're the president of the United States or you are the leader in that country and you are in this kind of a monetary crisis?
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): It's like anything, any fight. You don't want the internal fight. You want to get control and there's a fight for control. So we're living in a world today
Speaker 27 (lower-pitched voice): in which there are fights for control, right? Who has the power and the fights for
control?
Speaker 29 (lower-pitched voice): So again, though, at what point do we know the system is just broken? And this experience
Speaker 41: began post-war 1945 is like reached its end and we need
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): something. Pretty much almost only in retrospect.
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): what happens
if you're
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): really close up
and you say,
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): when did they know that there was a breakdown? Or when did they know that there was, let's say the French Revolution. There's a day that they say- -
Speaker 42: Storm of the Bastille.
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): - Right, and there's that day and they said
Speaker 12: it. They didn't know that.
Speaker 43: - No, they didn't. Just like some prison got raided or something. They didn't, yeah, no, that's right. -
Speaker 12: Okay.
Speaker 12: So when it's not like they announce it or
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): it becomes clear cut, right? You slip into those things, there's never that clear moment. But
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): what happens next? Like we heard Chairman Xi three days ago say, hey, by the way, China should hold the world's reserve currency. And that seems very far
away.
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): Now, I guess, but maybe.
Speaker 44: So you're asking me what I think about China's having.
Speaker 45: Well, the only reason I'm pointing that I have no idea if that's possible.
Speaker 44: I can respond to that. Tell me, yeah. Okay, I don't think China is going to have, there are two purposes of a
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): currency. Yes. Medium of exchange and storehold of wealth. Right. Okay.
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): Medium of exchange, it's logical that China is going to have much more of a medium of exchange type of reserve currency because it is right now the world's largest trading country.
Speaker 47: Right.
And
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): so people, central banks, want to hold some reserves in the things that they're trading in. Of course. And so on, and so they, the Chinese have intentionally,
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): In order to minimize that conflict, have not pushed that thing, and now they're going to operate and moving in that way. As far as storehold of wealth, though, who's going to trust the Chinese with your wealth and capital controls and so on? I think that all fiat currencies have a problem.
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): OK, so they have the history of foreign exchange controls. They have a would you trust it's anti wealth protection? You know, this is not that's not their great track record. I'm going to protect your wealth. You even private property and how it works in China is a new concept relatively. And it's something that they're, you know, wrestling about. They don't you can't own land. You know,
you can't own property.
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): property. So the storehold of wealth element is going to be very tough for them to sell. So the world does not have what you want as a currency, as a reserve currency, other than gold. I mean, it's just a default, right? Because it's a debt and gold is, like they
Speaker 27 (lower-pitched voice): say, it's the one asset you can have that's not somebody else's liability, meaning you have to get money from somebody else So I asked
Speaker 48: you last year off camera,
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): I'll never forget it. I've always been a gold buyer.
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): but then I don't know anything. It just instinctively seemed like it made sense. But I've always been a little bit embarrassed about it. And so I asked you, is it crazy to take some money and buy some gold? And you said it's not crazy at all. And I remember feeling vindicated, but also wondering, why don't more people say that? It almost feels like there was a conspiracy in the financial press. I
Speaker 49: think all around,
Speaker 11 (lower-pitched voice): not only in related to gold, but all of the things, I think people...
Speaker 11 (lower-pitched voice): Get
Speaker 12: used to What's credible to them is what they experience and the norm that they have at that time and So much see that's happening
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): you I hear people say I'm shocked by But the only reason they're shocked is because they become used to that right if you if you were a
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): traveling through time and you went and before 1971 and so on and you saw history and you saw the universal universality of money and gold and now the whole system worked repeatedly over time you would understand there's that dynamic that's taking place but yes people think they misunderstand
Speaker 11 (lower-pitched voice): they think it's a metal to speculate on
Speaker 11 (lower-pitched voice): they don't realize that actually
Speaker 12: it's a money, okay? Central banks,
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): second largest money, okay? So it's almost like when you look at the world through that money,
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): you can see what things cost through that lens. Exactly. People are looking at it instead like through a dollar lens and they see gold go up, okay? But that's not what they're looking at. Or you could look at the world through a gold lens and see money go down, okay?
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): So all I'm saying is because of their experience and what it is, it's implausible. It's like, you know, the tooth fairy or Santa Claus, you know, you believe in these things and so on, and then you realize through the cycle. And that's why surprises take place. That's why it seems implausible. But if you read history, it's almost...
You
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): know, it's it's logical
Speaker 51 (lower-pitched voice): most security systems operate like old-fashioned cable internet They're installed in one place. They're tied to one address and if you move or your job moves, you got to start over But that's not how other people do it construction sites ranches large properties. They have a better way They need cameras that are portable not tied down to one location Defend security cameras are the perfect solution for ordinary people and
to do
Speaker 51 (lower-pitched voice): this. With Defend, you own the camera. You're not renting it like a modem from a cable company. And you're not locked to a building or a wifi network. The job moves while then the camera moves with it. That's a better way to do things. No power lines or infrastructure of any kind is required.
Speaker 51 (lower-pitched voice): These run on cellular, like your phone. They're perfect for watching job site equipment overnight, livestock at your ranch, long driveways, outbuildings on your property. You mount it where you need it. You open the Defend app and you are set. You got clear footage, night vision, alerts straight to your phone. Defend never sells any data to anyone. Not tech companies, not the government, not China. Plans start at about five bucks a month. There's no contract. You can cancel at any time.
Speaker 51 (lower-pitched voice): Visit
Speaker 18 (lower-pitched voice): defendsellcam.com today, defendsellcam.com. So
Speaker 7 (lower-pitched voice): you don't seem surprised at all by anything that's happened or is happening right now. What are a few other things you would not
Speaker 29 (lower-pitched voice): be surprised to see in the near future? For example, let's start with gold. What would you not be surprised to see the spot price of gold per ounce in like five years?
I
Speaker 11 (lower-pitched voice): don't want to, you know, that's one of those...
Speaker 11 (lower-pitched voice): headline presuming...
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): Let me say it this way.
Speaker 52: Yes. I
think
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): people pay too much attention to the spot price and whether it's a spot going to go up or down or whatever. And what they don't do is think, if I didn't have any view on gold...
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): what amount should I have in my portfolio? In other words, if you did a portfolio construction exercise and you said, what is an effective diversified portfolio and what assets should I have and what amounts in that, because gold is a very effective diversifier and also a protector of this,
Speaker 27 (lower-pitched voice): during very bad times, gold does very well. When the rest of your portfolio does,
Speaker 27 (lower-pitched voice): poorly because let's say the 70s being a good example or the 30s being a good example during those times it's a diversifier
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): okay so the optimal amount to have for an individual or a
central bank
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): But an individual would be, depending on what's in their portfolio, between 5% and 15% of a portfolio. And so what I would say is if you approach that question that way and you think, what should I have? You should have what we talked about before, a year ago, I guess.
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): And so you should have that particular amount somewhere in that neighborhood, depending on what your portfolio is like and because it's an effect of diversifier and it is a money. OK, when the traditional money does badly, this money does well when the traditional money, which gives you an interest rate, then it's the reverse.
So
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): that's the thing that I would try to convey to people. Okay, do you have some of that? What's the amount that's your comfort level, but have some.
Speaker 54 (lower-pitched voice): So if
you
Speaker 7 (lower-pitched voice): were running the United States or a country like the United States in its current position, what would you need to do to protect your country in the midst of these changes? Some of which are inevitable, some of which maybe aren't.
Speaker 7 (lower-pitched voice): Like what are the
Man 1: steps specifically that you would take to
Speaker 55: help your country?
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): I would be dealing with achieve something like a 3% budget deficit.
Speaker 56 (lower-pitched voice): Not more than a 3% budget deficit. I would try to get financial,
I try to
Speaker 56 (lower-pitched voice): minimize,
or
Speaker 56 (lower-pitched voice): eliminate but minimize
Speaker 11 (lower-pitched voice): the risks of that dynamic I was talking about. So
Speaker 57: you would get the budget deficit of 3%.
Speaker 11 (lower-pitched voice): Yes, and I would say to every, I've said to
Speaker 56 (lower-pitched voice): legislators, I go
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): down to Washington and leaders of both parties. And I said, it's like being on a ship
Speaker 56 (lower-pitched voice): and everybody on the ship,
Is
Speaker 56 (lower-pitched voice): headed to a rock and that and everybody knows that if you have a deficit of 6 or 7% of GDP, you're going to have a supply demand problem. And I have the conversations and by and large, this is the agreement and I don't care whether you turn left or you turn right.
in
Speaker 56 (lower-pitched voice): terms of that, but do not hit the rock. And what if I would do is I would take a 3% pledge. In other words, say, I will get it down there. And if I can't agree on how, I would do it proportionately with three things. I would proportionately with taxes, spending. In other words, if you raised taxes by 4%, if you cut spending by 4%,
And
Speaker 56 (lower-pitched voice): you lowered, which would lower interest rates because it improved the supply demand and it would also convey the message that it's being dealt with. You would also lower the interest rate on the debt. And those two things would begin to get it to approach about a 3% budget deficit and so on. But doing that would require, would be politically impossible. So I have these conversations and the answer
is,
Speaker 56 (lower-pitched voice): is like, Ray, you don't understand the world of politics. If I'm, I have to give at least
one of two pledges,
Speaker 56 (lower-pitched voice): the pledges, and probably both. The pledges is, I won't raise your taxes and I won't cut your benefits.
Okay, you
Speaker 56 (lower-pitched voice): don't raise the taxes. So there's a big move here, primarily,
Speaker 56 (lower-pitched voice): to try to grow your way out of it in other words again you know stimulate fiscal and monetary stimulation and hope that that produces perhaps with the new technologies and so on that's the idea enough income growth
Speaker 56 (lower-pitched voice): And so on so that this moves toward that 3%, which is in my opinion a not likely occurrence.
Why
Speaker 30 (lower-pitched voice): is it not likely that technology will turn out to be so beneficial and
Speaker 58: lucrative that
it. I
Speaker 59 (lower-pitched voice): think that the
Speaker 56 (lower-pitched voice): artificial and technology miracle is a great miracle, okay? I mean, very, very beneficial.
Speaker 56 (lower-pitched voice): um and i've gone through studied great miracles the invention of electricity i mean wow what imagine where we'd be without that but if you anyway you know i could describe what the 20s would like and 2000s and like and so on um the ability to convert that to enough of a productivity miracle um is is not i think probable
In
Speaker 56 (lower-pitched voice): the also the time frame that we're dealing with. So this is an issue. The debt is and that dynamic remains an issue. And then, of course, what there is is the dynamic of of how that prosperity and productivity is shared. In other words, there's the it's it creates a great wealth gap.
Speaker 56 (lower-pitched voice): We'll talk about wealth. I'm going to come back and talk about wealth. But you're seeing great increases in wealth on some populations. Wow, trillionaire, okay? And that kind of thing. And then there's 60% of Americans have below a sixth grade reading level.
so that
Speaker 56 (lower-pitched voice): you take that sixth grade and okay now how are you going you still have to deal with the nature of that dynamic of how it comes so the question is what is the amount of productivity converted into income how does the government get that income to deal with its debt so the holders of the debt get a effective real return and don't have the problems how does that happen you know in a politically acceptable way there are lots of things that make that you know very very
difficult.
Speaker 56 (lower-pitched voice): difficult. I want to say something about wealth and wealth taxes, which is, I think, worth understanding. There's a big difference between wealth and money.
And I
Speaker 56 (lower-pitched voice): want to just highlight it, okay? Wealth is very
easy
Speaker 59 (lower-pitched voice): to create because it's almost accounting. Let
Speaker 56 (lower-pitched voice): me...
Speaker 56 (lower-pitched voice): What I mean by that is I could put out a raise 50 million dollars or individuals can raise 50 million dollars at a billion dollar valuation. And they will call that that that's that person's a billionaire and that there's a billion dollars more wealth.
OK, it's
Speaker 56 (lower-pitched voice): not literally that you have to have those transactions and wealth is not worth very much.
Speaker 56 (lower-pitched voice): unless you convert it to
money. In
Speaker 56 (lower-pitched voice): other words, you have all of that wealth, but you can't spend wealth.
Speaker 60: - You can't pay for dinner with it.
Speaker 56 (lower-pitched voice): - Right.
- Right. - You
Speaker 56 (lower-pitched voice): have to sell it, sell some of it in order to get money, in order to pay it. And so when wealth rises a lot relative to money,
Speaker 56 (lower-pitched voice): You have a risky situation. Okay. Now, the other thing about- Why is that a risky situation? Because when there's a movement, the bubbles pop. Right. When there's a movement that I need to get money. Now, that quite often is I need to get money because it's a debt service payment. In other words, let's say quite often people borrow to buy wealth.
Right.
Speaker 56 (lower-pitched voice): Okay. So there's a lot of borrowing now, not only in buying stock, but companies themselves buying to create wealth. And when you need to get the money, like in all the stock market bubbles, there was a lot of borrowing to buy the wealth. Well, when the need for money came along, they had to sell some of that wealth to get the money, and then that produces a dynamic.
Speaker 56 (lower-pitched voice): Well, you don't tax wealth, okay? So because you don't tax wealth, and then there is this political issue of wealth. Are you going to tax wealth? What is going to happen in California? What is going to happen elsewhere in terms of taxing wealth? If you tax wealth, then imagine what happens.
You have to
Speaker 56 (lower-pitched voice): sell wealth to pay taxes, okay?
Speaker 56 (lower-pitched voice): OK, so there's a dynamic
Speaker 39: understanding. And that lowers the value of it, right? And that's what pops bubbles, right?
So this
Speaker 56 (lower-pitched voice): the wealth issue is
is a
Speaker 56 (lower-pitched voice): political issue. The wealth gap issue is a political issue.
Speaker 56 (lower-pitched voice): And it's a market issue and it's important issue to understand.
Speaker 63: Is it inevitable that you would see given the way our wealth is allocated across 350
Speaker 64: million people that you would get the rise of wealth taxes? Because couldn't this have been predicted?
Speaker 44: It seems like it's such an obvious
Speaker 59 (lower-pitched voice): headline,
seemingly
Speaker 59 (lower-pitched voice): logical thing to do, right? In other words,
Speaker 56 (lower-pitched voice): everybody would say,
wait a
Speaker 56 (lower-pitched voice): second, all these people are having all the wealth and they're not paying any taxes on their wealth while this is going on. Okay, we need to go where the money is, right?
Speaker 65: Right.
So it
Speaker 56 (lower-pitched voice): seems like that without then...
Speaker 56 (lower-pitched voice): the full understanding of those things and how to do it in a managed way. But so it's, anyway, it's upon us, certainly. And what will
Speaker 66: happen? I mean, that's, I think, a referendum in California. Well,
Speaker 56 (lower-pitched voice): I think what's happening is, and we're seeing it around the world in many different ways, people are, people in California are moving.
Speaker 59 (lower-pitched voice): And...
Speaker 59 (lower-pitched voice): It's not the it happening, it's the fear of it happening.
Speaker 67 (lower-pitched voice): Right, right. So you're seeing that dynamic. I'm just like I'm a mechanic.
Of course, I get
Speaker 7 (lower-pitched voice): it, you're not judging either way. You're just describing what's happening. But because that is happening and people are moving and not just within the country but outside the country. Do you have any guesses or observations about where people are moving?
So
Speaker 30 (lower-pitched voice): clearly in the country, it's Texas, Florida, but Wyoming, but in the world, where are people moving?
Speaker 67 (lower-pitched voice): Generally speaking, they're moving to where there's civility and opportunity
Speaker 56 (lower-pitched voice): and there's not much fighting. They want to be in places that have a...
I
Speaker 56 (lower-pitched voice): don't know, they go to places that have lower taxation, but also vibrancy. You know, they go to Texas and Florida, as you say, and here in the Middle East or in places that are also vibrant and things are happening.
So
Speaker 56 (lower-pitched voice): you could see the patterns of those kinds of movements. And then the problems that that creates is a hollowing out in those places, the other places, because when they leave, the tax base is, you know, roughly speaking, you know, the top 10 percent.
Speaker 56 (lower-pitched voice): pays about 80% of 76% or something of the taxes. And so when you lose, let's say half of them, you lose a big amount of tax revenue, and then that becomes a dynamic.
Speaker 7 (lower-pitched voice): Could you see given all the factors you've described, like representative
Man 1: democracy continuing in a country like
ours?
And
Speaker 68: I,
Speaker 56 (lower-pitched voice): you
know, I
Speaker 56 (lower-pitched voice): just, I hope so. Oh, me too. I'm not, of course. And I just don't know. I think, yeah.
I
Speaker 56 (lower-pitched voice): think deep in us, we want, most Americans really, really want that and so on. And then at the same time, there are irreconcilable differences. And I think it was a recent poll, something like 25% of the population said that they would fight violently for their side. I mean, some significant percentage, yes.
Speaker 56 (lower-pitched voice): And so it only takes a relatively small amount. So I don't think we can take it for granted. In other words, there's a lot we can't take for granted. And I think we want to cherish those things, put those things above everything else. But you can't take it for granted.
Man 1: When you hear people speaking lightly of civil war, which they are, what's your reaction?
I
Speaker 56 (lower-pitched voice): have a principle, if you worry, you don't have to worry. And if you don't worry, you need to worry. Because if you worry- - You're pro-worry. - If you worry, then you're more inclined to prevent the thing that you're worried about.
So I
Speaker 56 (lower-pitched voice): think that the greater worry about some of these things is a good thing.
Speaker 56 (lower-pitched voice): In other words, okay, now we won't take it for granted. We worry about
Speaker 70: these things, so what are we going to do about
it? I
Speaker 7 (lower-pitched voice): see people not worrying and sort of blithely throwing it out. Almost like the way they talk about some foreign policy operations is go in and kill these guys, put these guys
Speaker 30 (lower-pitched voice): in, it'll be fine. That same attitude I hear a lot about the United States. Like, well, we're going to have to fight it out at some point. You've taken a close look at civil wars throughout history, what are they
like?
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): Well, civil wars and international
Speaker 56 (lower-pitched voice): wars are so horrendous that the most bold people who were, you know, trumpets blaring and going into that and so on, everyone came out of it with deep regret. I mean, we can see while we...
See
Speaker 56 (lower-pitched voice): it on the news and you can see that. But just imagine how horrendous the wars are. So I think it's a cycle, you know. Your confidence and your boldness is increased by the distance
Speaker 71: that you have to your last wars, you know. Right.
What
Speaker 7 (lower-pitched voice): is the difference,
Man 8: you were saying earlier, there's a difference between money and wealth. And wealth, you said, is not necessarily easily convertible to
money. In a
Speaker 72: society like ours, where is the money? Who has the money? Is it the same people who
have the wealth?
Speaker 73: No, no, no, no, no, many
Speaker 56 (lower-pitched voice): people
have,
Speaker 56 (lower-pitched voice): a lot of wealth and don't have much money. They have illiquid assets, okay? Money is that what you can transact. Currency, short-term deposits that you can assuredly and quickly turn into money, you know, that's what money is. And the central bank really controls the money. And then you could look at who has that,
Speaker 56 (lower-pitched voice): But increasingly, like you could look at M0, M1, and you could see money market accounts, and you could see those very liquid, you know, money, safe money, treasury bills, those kinds of things. And so that, you know, but ultimately it's the central bank because they control the supply demand. So,
I
Speaker 7 (lower-pitched voice): mean, if in a period of volatility, it would seem like the central bank would clamp down on the money supply circulating.
Speaker 7 (lower-pitched voice): among people
Speaker 31: well it faces the trade-off right the trade-off is
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): like in let's say COVID
right or in
Speaker 54 (lower-pitched voice): 1971 when there's too many claims and so on
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): there the trade-off is that people need money
And
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): they may need money to pay debt, and they may need money for whatever reasons. And so they are tempted, therefore, to create money. And so you see the coordination between fiscal policy and monetary policy. So you saw two big waves of large budget deficits and large supports of central banks, first under Trump when the COVID began, and then
Speaker 27 (lower-pitched voice): under Biden.
Speaker 27 (lower-pitched voice): biden when they got in and because he also wanted more universal basic income and both of those cases the government sent out lots of checks and that's also a popular thing to do discipline financial discipline is not what the population typically likes send out those checks but where does the money come from and then the central bank cooperates by buying the government bonds and you know, print money
Speaker 27 (lower-pitched voice): and then buying those bonds. So when they're in
Speaker 11 (lower-pitched voice): the middle, austerity is not an easy thing to have, right? What
happens if the
Speaker 74: government issues digital currency? What does that mean?
Speaker 25 (lower-pitched voice): Well, digital currency is... Right, you're
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): talking about central bank digital currencies. Yeah. Okay, and that...
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): There's a great deal of appeal because of the fact that it's easy and so on. But it's, and I think it'll be done, a lot happens. You think it will be done? Yeah, I think it's, but what happens in the digital currency,
of
Speaker 27 (lower-pitched voice): course, it's easy to transact and so on. Almost, and it'll be like money market funds,
I think.
Speaker 27 (lower-pitched voice): The question will be first, will they be able to offer interest? So there's a debate now as to whether they will be interest. If they're not able to offer interest and they there will be a debate probably they won't be. But then they're not on effective vehicle to hold it in because you have the depreciation course. You'd rather hold it in a money market fund or a bond, but that's the bait.
Speaker 27 (lower-pitched voice): There will be no privacy and it's a very effective controlling mechanism by the government. What I mean is all the transactions will be known, all transactions done with digital currencies will be known, which is good for illegal activities, getting control of illegal activities. But it also means that the government has a great deal of control. For example, they can tax that way, they can take your money.
Speaker 27 (lower-pitched voice): they can establish foreign exchange controls and the like. So that's something
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): that will be an increasing issue, particularly for international holders of that currency because
Speaker 27 (lower-pitched voice): they might feel, let's say if you're a Frenchman and they wanted to have
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): sanctions, they could take your money and so on. So there's the privacy issue of that.
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): And if you're
Speaker 20: politically disfavored, you could be shut
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): off. Politically disfavored, you could be shut off, yes. So those kinds of issues enter into it. For those reasons, and they're very tiny. I don't think that you're going to see the development of central bank digital currencies to be of a magnitude that it's going to be that big of a deal.
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): I think that doesn't mean it won't grow,
Speaker 54 (lower-pitched voice): but I don't think it's going to be a big deal, so. -
So
Speaker 7 (lower-pitched voice): my last question is given your description of the United States as in stage five, in a process that only- - Which
Speaker 25 (lower-pitched voice): doesn't mean it's inevitable.
Speaker 7 (lower-pitched voice): - Of course.
But
Speaker 7 (lower-pitched voice): there are only six stages in the process you described. So it's toward the terminus.
Speaker 25 (lower-pitched voice): It's the time that it's time to worry.
So you go
Speaker 7 (lower-pitched voice): to Washington, you try to convince policymakers, members of Congress, people, administration,
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): here's what you need to do. You've described the reception you get is like, hey, you don't understand politics, we can't do that. So that's not a lot of headway made, obviously, for obvious
reasons. Do
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): you have advice for people watching who are not policymakers, who are just
Americans,
as to
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): what they can do to prepare for whatever comes
next?
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): Well, there's the basics. Well,
earn
Speaker 54 (lower-pitched voice): more than you spend, try to save, diversify your portfolio, including about money.
And those
Speaker 54 (lower-pitched voice): things are of paramount importance.
Speaker 54 (lower-pitched voice): think about the country, the opportunities. Where are the opportunities?
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): People have
Speaker 27 (lower-pitched voice): migrated from one place to another.
Follow the opportunities. And
Speaker 27 (lower-pitched voice): most importantly
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): is raise your children well, so that they're well-educated and able to be productive and also civil so that they can be...
be
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): effective and as I say there are only three things a country needs to do and that's the same for the individuals you know raise your kids well so that they're well educated and can earn an income and and operate go to places that work well so that they there's civility and productivity and there's opportunity and stay out of civil wars and international
wars
Those seem
Speaker 76: pretty obvious. You
do
Speaker 71: those things well? I mean, really, almost everything else takes care of itself. Really. Yeah. Ray
Dalio, thank you
Speaker 77: very much for that. It's always a pleasure. Thank you.